Leandro is an amazing guy in a slum in Rio, and he created a recycling project in the slum. At the end of last year, December 16, he received an eviction order by the Rio de Janeiro state government giving him two weeks to leave the space that he had been using for two years. The plan was to hand it over to a developer, who planned to turn it into a construction site. Leandro started a campaign using one of our tools, the Pressure Cooker, the same one that Bia and Jovita used, and the state government changed their minds before Christmas Eve. These stories make me happy, but not just because they have happy endings. They make me happy because they are happy beginnings. The teacher and parent community at Bia's school is looking for other ways they could improve that space even further. Leandro has ambitious plans to take his model to other low-income communities in Rio, and Jovita is volunteering at the police unit that she helped created. Bia, Jovita and Leandro are living examples of something that citizens and city governments around the world need to know: We are ready. As citizens, we are ready to decide on our common destinies, because we know that the way we distribute power says a lot about how we actually value everyone, and because we know that enabling and participating in local politics is a sign that we truly care about our relations to one another, and we are ready to do this in cities around the world right now. With the Our Cities network, the Meu Rio team hopes to share what we have learned with other people who want to create similar initiatives in their own cities. We have already started doing it in São Paulo with incredible results, and want to take it to cities around the world through a network of citizen-centric, citizen-led organizations that can inspire us, challenge us, and remind us to demand real participation in our city lives. It is up to us to decide whether we want schools or parking lots, community-driven recycling projects or construction sites, loneliness or solidarity, cars or buses, and it is our responsibility to do that now, for ourselves, for our families, for the people who make our lives worth living, and for the incredible creativity, beauty, and wonder that make our cities, in spite of all of their problems, the greatest invention of our time. Obrigado. Thank you. (Applause)
Leandro es una persona increíble de un barrio pobre en Río. Creó un proyecto de reciclaje en su barrio. A finales del año pasado, el 16 de diciembre, recibió una orden de desalojo del gobierno de Río de Janeiro que le daba 2 semanas para desalojar el espacio que había estado usando durante 2 años. El plan era entregarlo a un desarrollador que iba a construir ahí. Leandro empezó una campaña usando una de nuestras herramientas, la olla de presión, de la misma manera en que la usaron Bia y Jovita y nuestro gobierno cambió sus planes antes de Navidad. Estas historias me hacen feliz, pero no solo porque tiene un final feliz. Me hacen feliz porque tiene un comienzo feliz. Los profesores y padres de la escuela de Bia están buscando la manera de mejorar ese espacio aún más. Leandro tiene planes ambicioso para llevar su modelo a otras comunidades de bajos ingresos en Río y Jovita es voluntaria en la unidad policial que ayudó a crear. Bia, Jovita y Leandro son ejemplos vivientes de algo que los ciudadanos y los gobiernos alrededor del mundo necesitan saber: Estamos listos. Como ciudadanos estamos listos para decidir nuestro destino común, porque sabemos que la manera en que repartimos el poder dice mucho acerca de lo que en realidad le importa a todos, y porque sabemos que participar en las políticas locales es una señal clara de que nos importan nuestras relaciones entre nosotros y estamos listos para esto en las ciudades alrededor del mundo hoy mismo. Con la red Nuestras Ciudades, el equipo de Meu Rio desea compartir lo que hemos aprendido con otras personas que deseen crear iniciativas similares en sus propias ciudades. Ya lo empezamos a hacer en Sao Paulo. con resultados increíbles y queremos llevarlo a todas las ciudades del mundo a través de una red centrada en los ciudadanos de organizaciones dirigidas por ciudadanos que nos inspiren, que nos estimulen y que nos recuerden exigir participación real en nuestras ciudades. Depende de nosotros decidir si queremos escuelas o estacionamientos, proyectos comunitarios de reciclaje u obras de construcción, soledad o solidaridad, autos o autobuses y es nuestra responsabilidad hacerlo hoy, por nosotros, por nuestras familias, por las personas que hacen que nuestras vidas valgan la pena vivirse y por la creatividad increíble, por la belleza y la maravilla que hacen de nuestras ciudades, a pesar de sus problemas, la mayor invención de nuestra era. Obrigado. Gracias. (Aplausos)